ד' דף ל"ד, Daled, daf lamed daled,
and we pick up on the top of ל"ג עמוד ב'. lamed
gimmel amud bais. Let's see, I think today we actually might be
able to close the gap. And we're dealing with right now in
the middle of the issue about כבוד הרב, kavod harav, and we
just had the statement that we'll take it from the very top
of ל"ג עמוד ב'. lamed gimmel amud bais. This is a statement
in the name of רב איבו אמר רב ינאי: Rav Aivo amar
Rav Yannai: אין תלמיד חכם רשאי לעמוד מפני רבו. ain talmid chacham
rishai la'amod mipnei rabbo. תלמיד חכם Talmid chacham is not allowed, although
תוספות Tosafos says רשאי rishai here means not required, to stand up
in the before his רבי, Rebbe,
אלא שחרית וערבית. ella shacharis v'arvis. Only morning and evening, כדי שלא
יהא כבודו מרובה מכבוד שמים, k'dai shelo yei kvodo merubeh mi'kvod shamayim,
so it shouldn't be greater than the honor afforded to heaven, where
it's only again funny, two times, although it's three times if we're
talking about דאוונען, davening, which presumably we are, but okay, let's say
you do maybe this is an indication that they used to do
an early מנחה מעריב mincha maariv together or קביעת מעריב רשות k'vias
maariv reshus or something, I don't know, anyway.
תוספתא Tosefta says רשאי rishai does mean
allowed.
כדי, K'dai, that's a good point, that's a good point, כדי, k'dai,
that's a very good point. You know,
that's a very good point, you're right, this one does sound more
like it's in the sense of permitted, that it should not
be that it should not be more than what we do for
God. All right, that's a good point. מתיב, Meisiv, says the גמרא,
Gemara, I'll ask you on this: רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר מנין
לזקן שלא יטריח, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer, minayin l'zaken shelo yatriach,
how do you know, you know, a sage should not cause a
burden on people? תלמוד לומר זקן ויראת, Talmud lomar zaken v'yareisa, so
that he has to, you know, even he has to be fearful
of God and not overdo the honor due to him. ואם אמרת
שחרית וערבית בלבד אמאי לא נטרח? V'im amarta shacharis v'arvis bilvad, amai
lo nitrach? חיובא הוא. Chiyuva hu. So if it's only, you know,
then, you know, that morning and evening, why should he not cause
them the burden? Meaning if they haven't done it morning and evening,
then that's their obligation, and if they've already going to do it
morning and evening, then walking in people's presence won't cause any greater
obligation than the basic two, right? We're not talking about more than
two, so what's the big deal? אלא לאו כולי יומא, Ella lav,
kulei yoma, so you see that it's not true, that anytime in
the day that you see your רבי Rebbe you have to stand.
גמרא Gemara says לא לעולם שחרית וערבית בלבד. lo, l'olam shacharis v'arvis
bilvad. No, we were talking just about morning and evening. ואפילו הכי
כמה דאפשר ליה לא נטרח, V'afilo hachi, kama d'efshar lei lo nitrach,
and even so, even if it's just that morning and evening, still
if it's possible don't even cause people to stand even for that
minimum amount. Find a way to go around not to even, you
know, make them have to do that. Okay, so
that's the end of that. Now take a look at תוספות Tosafos
though. תוספות Tosafos says, you know, it's not so black and white.
It's also interesting that it starts with אין תלמיד חכם רשאי לעמוד
מפני רבו. ain talmid chacham rishai la'amod mipnei rabbo. Why does it
specifically say about a תלמיד חכם? talmid chacham? And why does it
say רבו? rabbo? Why, right, we're talking about standing before any sage
or whatever, right? Or I mean that's this whole question going on
in this גמרא, Gemara, is it specifically your רבי, Rebbe, is it
any sage? But still why does it say תלמיד חכם? talmid chacham?
So תוספות, Tosafos, maybe it's even a תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. But
let's look at what תוספות Tosafos says. אין תלמיד חכם רשאי לעמוד
מפני רבו שחרית וערבית, Ain talmid chacham rishai la'amod mipnei rabbo shacharis
v'arvis, says תוספות. Tosafos. תימה למה הקפיד רבא לעיל שמא קמו מפניו
שחרית וערבית ולאו אדעתיה? Teima, lama hikpid Rava l'eyl shema kamu mipanav
shacharis v'arvis v'lav adaiteih? Why did רבא Rava get upset when he
passed by the students that were on the other side of the
river that they weren't standing for him? Maybe they did stand for
him in the morning and in the evening. Maybe they saw him
in the morning. It wasn't yet the evening, they would stand for
him in the evening, you know, and maybe he just, and even
if he didn't see them stand for him in the morning, maybe
he wasn't aware, you know, that they had stood for him in
the morning. So how could, you know, how is he getting so
upset? ונראה לפרש דדין זה אינו נוהג אלא לגבי אותם הדרים בבית
הרב. V'nira l'fareish d'din zeh eino noheig ella l'gabbei osam hadarin b'veis
harav. No, we're talking about people that are like living in the
רבי's Rebbe house or what we might say is like students in
a ישיבה yeshiva where they're seeing the רביים rabbeim the whole day.
Okay, you're seeing רביים rabbeim the whole day. Every time the רבי
Rebbe walks in and out of the room you stand up? So
the גמרא Gemara says דמסתמא עמדו שחרית וערבית. d'mistama amdu shacharis v'arvis.
אבל תלמידים אחרים חייבים לעמוד אפילו מאה פעמים ביום. Aval talmidim acheirim
chayavim la'amod afilu meiah p'amim bayom. But other students, even if it's
a תלמיד-רבי talmid-rebbe relationship, right? If it's not like you're in the
constant presence, it's a nice analogy to God. You're constantly in the
presence of God, right? So if you're not in the constant presence,
so even if he's like dropping in and out, but nevertheless, you
know, it's still
אפילו מאה פעמים ביום. afilu meiah p'amim bayom. שמא יראה אחר ויחשדם,
Shema yeira'eh acheir v'yechashedeim, מכל
מקום, m'koaz, somebody will see the רבי Rebbe walking into the room
and nobody stood. What is this? You guys don't show respect for
your רבי? Rebbe And presumably if they're regularly there, somebody won't have
that חשד, chashad, that suspicion. ואפילו אותם שדרים בבית הרב נמי אם
באו פנים חדשות צריכים לעמוד. V'afilu osam shedarin b'veis harav nami im
ba'u panim chadashos tzrichim la'amod. And תוספות Tosafos even says no, more
than that. The only reason you don't have to stand if you're
all together in the ישיבה yeshiva is because everybody's in it together.
So everybody knows that everybody else stood earlier in the day. But
if you have a visitor come to the ישיבה, yeshiva, then everybody
needs to stand for the רבי Rebbe? to show the respect he
shows the רבי. Rebbe So it's very interesting this idea about חשד,
chashad, but you know one could also tie the idea of חשד
chashad to the idea of כבוד, kavod, because כבוד kavod is also
how, you know, of respect. shown in a public sphere, not just
between the two people. I mean, I can show you honor and
nobody else could be around, but there's also sort of like the
גמרא Gemara also about in the bathroom, there's certain types of social
realities in which these parameters change. Okay, so that's the way תוספות
Tosfos understands it. If you're already making this distinction, you could make
it the other way as I said, whether it's like a new
event or not a new event. Think about the example about like
it's in the middle of a thunderstorm, right? And every time you
see lightning, every time you see thunder, you have to make a
ברכה? Bracha? The answer is no. The answer is only if it's
all the same storm you don't have to, even though you're sort
of experiencing the thunder and lightning each time. But if the clouds
scatter and then it starts raining again, then you do. So anyway,
it's interesting. תוספות Tosfos trying to put a balance between this statement
and it doesn't really seem that way from certain other גמרות. Gemaras.
Yes.
Is there any ענין inyan of standing for your parents?
Well, it doesn't say that you do. It's like לא ישב במקומו
lo yeshev bimkomo or מכריע את דבריו. machria et devarav.
Right. Right. I mean, the גמרא Gemara didn't say, right, אינו עומד
במקומו. eino omed bimkomo. There was a גמרא Gemara before about I
think right, somebody said that when he heard his mother coming, he
says the שכינה's Shechinah coming and he stood up. But I think
in terms of like a strict requirement, you're right, it's not. It's
only for the רבי, Rebbe. which is going to be interesting because
we're going to get to this issue about כבוד kavod parents and
כבוד kavod the רבי Rebbe, and we're going to get to it
in a minute. So let's take a look. Okay. אמר רבי אלעזר:
Amar Rabbi Elazar: כל תלמיד חכם שאינו עומד מפני רבו נקרא רשע.
kol talmid chacham she-eino omed mipnei rabbo nikra rasha. If you don't
do it, you're called a רשע. rasha. Okay? ואינו מאריך ימים. ve-eino
maarich yamim. And you don't have long days. ותלמודו משתכח. ve-talmudo mishtakeiach.
And you forget your own תורה. Torah. שנאמר: she-ne'emar: וטוב לא יהיה
לרשע. ve-tov lo yihiyeh lara-sha. And there will not be good, which
is understood to be like תורה, Torah, because what else is good
for a תלמיד חכם? talmid chacham? For the wicked person, so he's
called a
רשע. rasha. ולא יאריך ימים, ve-lo yaarich yamim, כצל אשר איננו ירא
מלפני
אלוהים katzel asher einennu yaray milifnei Elokim like as a shade, like
it'll be very ephemeral, אשר איננו ירא מלפני אלוהים, asher einennu yaray
milifnei Elokim, and he does not have fear before God. מורא זו
איני יודע מה הוא? mora zo eini yodeia mah hu? What is
this fear? כשהוא אומר keshe-hu omer ויראת מאלוהיך הרי מורא זו קימה.
ve-yareta mei-Elokecha harei mora zo kima. It means standing up. And as
תוספות Tosfos points out also that standing up? What? Because it's the
end of the פסוק pasuk of right, the end of the פסוק
pasuk of
והדרת פני זקן ויראת מאלוהיך. vehadarta pnei zaken ve-yareta mei-Elokecha. Now the
גמרא Gemara says, but there's a number of places that it says
ויראת מאלוהיך. ve-yareta mei-Elokecha. ואימא מורא ריבית? ve-eima mora ribit? Like about
ריבית ribit that it says like לא תקח מאתו נשך ותרבית ויראת
מאלוהיך, lo tikach mei-ito neshech ve-tarbit ve-yareta mei-Elokecha, right? ומורא משקלות, u-mora
mishkalot, and the weights. Now the problem with the weights is right,
it says like אבני צדק והין צדק avnei tzedek vehin tzedek whatever,
it doesn't say ויראת מאלוהיך. ve-yareta mei-Elokecha. So תוספות Tosfos says well
maybe it's because by עמלק Amalek is juxtaposed to the משקלות mishkalot
and by עמלק Amalek it says ולא ירא אלוהים, ve-lo yarei Elokim,
right? So in דברים, Devarim, it speaks about the אבני צדק והין
צדק avnei tzedek vehin tzedek and then it speaks about זכור את
אשר עשה לך עמלק. zachor et asher asa lecha Amalek. So that's
the and עמלק Amalek was ולא ירא אלוהים. lo yarei Elokim. Although
תוספות Tosfos has another brilliant read of what משקלות mishkalot means, which
תוספות Tosfos has a גרסא, girsa, well, it's not really a question
of read, but a גרסא. girsa. Not משקלות, mishkalot, but מכשלות. michshalot.
And it's לא תתן מכשול ויראת מאלוהיך. lo titein michshal ve-yareta mei-Elokecha.
So putting a stumbling block before somebody else. Anyway, רבי אלעזר Rabbi
Elazar so anyway, but there's other places it says
ויראת מאלוהיך. ve-yareta mei-Elokecha. רבי אלעזר: Rabbi Elazar: פני פני גמר. pnei
pnei gemar. No, because here it says מלפני האלוהים milifnei ha-Elokim and
it says והדרת פני זקן. vehadarta pnei zaken. Also one could speak
about the fact that the fear of God is tied the whole
idea מורא רבך כמורא שמים, moras rabcha ke-mora shamayim, it's not just
the juxtaposition of ויראת מאלוהיך. ve-yareta mei-Elokecha. Part of this has to
do with a type of a honor and fear and awe reverence
shown
towards תורה Torah and towards religious achievement, towards somebody that sort of
represents something godly. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this:
תא שמע. ta shema. Now of course again, the funny thing is
why do you have to say it by a תלמיד חכם? talmid
chacham? Say anybody who doesn't show מורא בפני רבו. mora bifnei rabbo.
And again, the question is, is it because a תלמיד חכם talmid
chacham might be think like oh, I'm such a big תלמיד חכם
talmid chacham myself, like I why do I have to show כבוד
kavod here, I know as much as him or whatever, there could
be that issue, right? Or there could be the idea that like
so therefore like the תלמיד חכם talmid chacham maybe would be more
inclined not to do it, right? Like has a little יצר הרע
yetzer hara not to do it, so maybe that's why we have
to say that if a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham does not do
it but
or maybe again maybe it's like it's more of
a פגיעה pgiya on
דכבוד התורה de-kavod ha-Torah that somebody is that somebody's sort of
who really like appreciates what this תורה Torah is and is not
showing it. There's different ways of framing it. Or, and here's really
the one thing that I wanted to say, is that again how
much has the emphasis shifted from פני זקן, pnei zaken, which is
any sort of תורה Torah sage, to this issue of רבו? rabbo?
So the reason it might be talking about תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
is maybe it's not saying like oh, a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
might have a יצר הרע yetzer hara not to stand and even
he though will be punished or whatever. Maybe it's actually saying that
דוקא תלמיד חכם davka talmid chacham because he has a רבי-תלמיד relationship.
Somebody who doesn't stand before סתם stam sage, all right, that's a
problem, but it's like a particular problem with somebody who has this
רבי-תלמיד relationship and he's actually violating that. What did you want to
say though?
I was just going to say that
ותלמודו משתכח, ve-talmudo mishtakeiach, of course, that
only applies to a תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. Right, that's relevant to
a תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. Yeah, so again I think that the
interesting question here is: is the גמרא Gemara emphasizing the heightened responsibility
with a תלמיד-רבי relationship, or is it sort of saying like even
a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, or a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham might
have a greater like somehow יצר הרע yetzer hara not to stand.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. איבעיא
להו.
Ibaya
lehu. They asked the question. בנו והוא רבו. Beno vehu rabbo. And
now we get exactly to this, the issue about כיבוד רב kibbud
rav and כיבוד, kibbud, you know, כיבוד אב ואם. kibbud av va'em.
Now it is true by the way, you know, what's important to
sort of know in the background is that the famous גמרא Gemara
says that if a person has to choose between returning a lost
object to his רבי Rebbe or to his father, because he finds
an object on the street or whatever he can only pick up
one of them, right, he returns it to his רבי rebbe because
his father brought him into this world and his רבי rebbe brings
him לעולם הבא. le'olam haba. Right, and there's a certain priority given.
So that sort of would incline one to think that כיבוד רב
kibbud rav is going to trump כיבוד אב ואם. kibbud av va'em.
Okay, but that's if you have to choose, like do I give
honor to my father or do I give honor to my רבי?
rebbe But what if they're like in opposite, going in opposite directions
because the student is the רבי rebbe of the father? Okay, so
it's not just like you're passively, you know, prioritizing one over the
other. It's actually if the father will now stand for the son
because the son is his רבי, rebbe is that actually
undermining the whole institution of כיבוד אב? kibbud av? You know what
I'm saying? It's not just choosing one, it's to make the father
the one who gives honor to the son is actually, you know,
directly opposite the whole relationship of כיבוד אב ואם. kibbud av va'em.
So that's going to be the question. So let's take a look.
איבעיא להו. Ibaya lehu. So they raised the question. בנו והוא רבו.
Beno vehu rabbo. If somebody's son is his רבי. rebbe? מהו לעמוד
מפני אביו? Mah lo'amod mipnei aviv?
So does the son stand for the father? And we're going to
ask the other question in a minute: does the father stand for
the son? But let's ask each question separately. Does the son stand
for his father if the son is the רבי? rebbe So the
גמרא Gemara says תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear. אמר ליה
שמואל לרב יהודה, Amar lei Shmuel leRav Yehuda, שמואל Shmuel said to
רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, שיננא, Shinana, קום מקמי אבוך. kum mikmei avuch.
Now if you'll remember before רב יהודה Rav Yehuda was the one
who corrected his father רב יחזקאל Rav Yechezkel who was teaching this,
you know, this thing about נסקלין בנסרפין niskalin benisrafim and he says
"don't teach it this way, teach it that way." And then שמואל
Shmuel said back to him, "שיננא, Shinana, hey you think you're so
sharp, you know, don't speak to your father that way." People remember
that story? Right. So anyway, so he needed a little lesson about
כיבוד אב ואם, kibbud av va'em, but nevertheless it was clear that
he was the רבי rebbe, and his father was the תלמיד. talmid
And nevertheless what did שמואל Shmuel say to him? קום מקמי אבוך.
kum mikmei avuch. So שמואל's Shmuel very consistent. Wants to keep יהודה
Yehuda in his, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda in his place and teach
him "you might be smarter but talk to your father the right
way, stand before your father" and so on. So you see that
even if the son is the רבי, rebbe. the son has to,
that doesn't mean that the son doesn't do his obligation of כיבוד
אב ואם. kibbud av va'em. He still has to recognize that his
father is his father.
Standing in front of the father.
Oh you know what, that's a good point. That's a good point
that the גמרא Gemara is actually assuming that the,
right, this obligation of standing.
Yeah, that's a good point. Okay, let's get back to that. But
let's read this further. So the גמרא Gemara says no. So the
גמרא Gemara says שאני רב יחזקאל דבעל מעשים הוה. Sha'ani Rav Yechezkel
deba'al ma'asim hava. No no no. רב יחזקאל Rav Yechezkel wasn't just
his father. רב יחזקאל Rav Yechezkel had a special obligation to stand
for him because he was like רב יחזקאל Rav Yechezkel who was
רב יהודה's Rav Yehuda father. No no no, רב יחזקאל Rav Yechezkel
was the father. רב יחזקאל Rav Yechezkel wasn't סתם, stam, it wasn't
just because he was the father, רב יחזקאל Rav Yechezkel also was
like a big חסיד. chassid. בעל מעשים Ba'al ma'asim is like he
was a person of great, you know, religious deeds, you know, great
righteous deeds. And therefore that demanded respect. So even in the sort
of תורה Torah religious realm there was, you know, there
was רב יהודה Rav Yehuda might have been the תלמיד חכם, talmid
chacham, but he was like the צדיק. tzaddik. Okay so therefore that
made the situation different. Okay. They were more religious equals in that
way. ואפילו מר שמואל Ve'afillu Mar Shmuel קדי kadei and שמואל Shmuel
himself נאי na'i קמיה מקמיה. kamei mikamei. Even שמואל, Shmuel, who told
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda to stand before him, but שמואל Shmuel would
stand before רב יחזקאל. Rav Yechezkel. So it didn't have to do
with the fact that רב יחזקאל Rav Yechezkel was the father, had
to do with רב יחזקאל Rav Yechezkel himself was a, you know,
was worthy of that honor of standing in front of him. Okay,
so גמרא Gemara says אלא מאי קאמר ליה? Ella mai ka'amar lei?
So that's true, what's the point of telling him "hey stand before
your father"? It's not because stand before your father, it seems like
it's a
חידוש chiddush in הלכות כיבוד אב ואם. hilchot kibbud av va'em. According
to this it's just because, you know, this person is a, you
know, great accomplished
person in the world of מעשים טובים ma'asim tovim and, you know,
and מצוות. mitzvot. So the גמרא Gemara says no. הכי קאמר ליה.
Hachi ka'amar lei. This is what he's saying to him. זימני דאתי
מאחוריי, Zimnei de'asi me'achurai, קום מקמיה kuma mikamei ולא תיחוש ליקרא דידי.
velo teichosh liyikra didi. Sometimes your father will be coming behind me
and, you know, and even if like you've already stood for me
and you think that to stand for him in my presence will
be disrespectful to my honor—שמואל Shmuel talking to רב יהודה—don't Rav Yehuda
worry about that. Still stand for him. Okay, but it's a very
funny reread. So what, it's a, you know, it's about some totally
new idea about standing before somebody who's a צדיק, tzaddik, you know,
and even in the presence of your רבי rebbe? standing. So what?
It's you know, it's like about some totally new idea about standing
before somebody who's a צדיק, tzadik, you know, and even in the
presence of your רבי, rebbe stand before somebody who's a צדיק. tzadik.
It didn't sound like that. It sounded like it was a חידוש
chidush in הלכות כיבוד אב ואם. Hilchos Kibbud Av Va'Eim. Okay, but
the גמרא Gemara somehow managed to bracket that. Let's keep on going.
תא שמע, Ta Shma, come and hear. I'm sorry, did I skip
a line? איבעיא להו, Iba'ya lehu, so we don't have an answer
to that question. Next question: בנו והוא רבו מהו שיעמוד אביו מפניו.
Beno vehu rabbo mahu sheya'amod aviv mipanav.
So we don't know if the son stands for the father, but
now we want to know would the father stand for the son?
So is there still going to be, you know, is when the
son is a big תלמיד חכם, Talmid Chacham, does he have to
show כבוד אב, Kevod Av, or is that undermining his status as
a רבי rebbe, and as a תורה Torah scholar? And vice-versa: when
the father is the student, does he have to show כבוד רב,
Kevod Rav, or is that undermining his role as the father? Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this, so תא שמע, Ta Shma,
come and hear, דאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, De'amar Rabbi Yehoshua Ben
Levi, אני איני כדאי לעמוד מפני בני אלא משום כבוד בית הנשיא.
Ani eini kedai la'amod mifnei beni ela mishum kevod beis haNasi.
I really am do not, you know, should not have to stand
before my son because he's not a big תלמיד חכם, Talmid Chacham,
but I stand before him because he's connected to the house of
the נשיא, Nasi, presumably by marriage I guess or by political connections,
not by birth because then I would also be. Anyway, and that's
why I stand because he's obviously, you know, of his sort of
a political status. So the גמרא Gemara says טעמא דאנא רבי, Taima
de'ana Rebbi,
the reason is because I'm the רבי. rebbe הא איהו רבאי, Ha
ihu rabbai, if he was my רבי, Rebbe, קמינא מקמיה, kamina mikamei,
I would stand before him. Right? The implication is I don't stand
before him because of his תורה Torah knowledge, I stand before him
because of his political connections. But it sounds like if he did
have the תורה Torah knowledge, the father would stand before the son.
So the גמרא Gemara says הכי קאמר, Hachi ka'amar, אני איני כדאי
לעמוד מפני בני ואפילו הוא רבאי דאנא
אבוה. Ani eini kedai la'amod mifnei beni ve'afilu hu rabbai de'ana avuha.
I really shouldn't have to stand before my son even if he
was my רבי Rebbe because I'm the father. Father should never stand
before the son in all cases. אלא משום כבוד בית הנשיא, Ela
mishum kevod beis haNasi, but only because he's connected to the בית
הנשיא. Beis HaNasi. So basically we have no answer. Right? We tried
to bring a proof, each thing sort of suggested the simple פשט
Pshat of each thing was that the son stands for the father,
you know, if the son is the רבי, Rebbe. and the father
stands for the son when the son is the רבי. Rebbe, And
we had a way to push off both of those proofs. So
what are you left with? So the ראש Rosh and therefore the
שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch פוסק poskens here, Michael for once I'll actually
discuss פסק psak because Michael always says what's the פסק? psak? Okay,
so the ראש Rosh and the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch פוסק poskens
is very interesting. The ראש, Rosh, I'm seeing if I can pull
up the רמ"א. Rama. The ראש Rosh and the שולחן ערוך Shulchan
Aruch פוסק poskens that it's a what do you call it, that
each,
that they both stand for one another. At the same time? Yeah,
like I don't know how that would happen, but which I guess
if one walks into the room then the other one stands up,
but I'm not exactly sure how to synchronize it, but both are
obligated to show respect to one another. So which is a nice
idea, which means like, and it's a nice idea when you're saying
both of them at the same time. Like because if you only
said it in one direction, you're left with the problem that if,
you know, the father stands for the son but not vice versa,
he's losing his status of the father, right? But if the son
is also standing for him, both statuses are acknowledged. Or the reverse,
right, if the son, you know, what would be the case? I
say father, if the son stands for the father and the father
not for the son, then it undermines the כבוד kavod that's due
to תורה Torah and the son's status as רבי, Rebbe right? So
to say just one is a problem, but to say both allows
both of them to, you know, to both statuses to be acknowledged.
רמב"ם, Rambam, however, interestingly,
rules, I'll pull up the רמב"ם. Rambam. רמב"ם Rambam here rules: ואף
על פי שהיה תלמיד בנו
אין האב עומד מפני הבן אבל הבן עומד מפני אביו אף על
פי שהוא תלמידו. Ve'af al pi shehaya
talmid beno ein
ha'av omed mifnei haben aval haben omed mifnei aviv af al pi
shehu talmido.
Okay,
so the רמב"ם Rambam is actually quite interesting. Right? The father-son relationship,
even though the הלכה Halacha is you return your רבי's Rebbe, אבידה
aveida before your father's אבידה, aveida, right, I think there's something like
fundamental that like, that like at the end of the day, you
know, the, you know, you can't do something, you can't put the
father in a subservient or lower status relationship to the son, right,
even if the son is the רבי. Rebbe. So the father, he
always has, just the son stands for the father and not the
other way around.
Well, I would see it as that
inherent in the כבוד התורה Kevod HaTorah that's due to the, to
the רבי Rebbe, is a humility that, you know, that still he
has a father. You know, that's part of his תורה, Torah, part
of the, you know.
So it's the acknowledgment that I got all of this from my
father you mean, or do you mean sort of like that part
of representing תורה Torah is representing the מצוה mitzvah of כיבוד אב?
Kibbud Av?
Right. Whereas the מצוה mitzvah of כיבוד אב Kibbud Av is, it
seems to be, seems to me like a more universal thing that
is, you know,
I wouldn't say apart from תורה, Torah, but is a reality that
does not acknowledge necessarily the existence or the primacy of תורה. Torah.
It's like it exists independently. Right.
No, I like that idea that part of the whole, the תורה
Torah that you represent, you know, has to show. It's sort of
like somebody who learns we're going to get to it later you
know, הלומד שלא על מנת לעשות. Halomed Shelo Manat La'asot. Right. What
does your learning mean if it doesn't translate into action? If you're
representing תורה, Torah, then one of the things that תורה Torah is
about is showing, you know, כיבוד אב. Kibbud Av. Right. Right. That's
very beautiful. Okay. Yeah.
The רבי Rebbe can bring the student into this world to come,
but the father had only brought this child into this world.
That's true in general, but even acknowledging that, we still say when
you choose between one, you choose the רבי. Rebbe. So it's very
powerful here, I think, that the רמב"ם Rambam is saying but if
there's somehow in conflict, which status has to be, you know, performed
like if one is being challenged, if only one status is, you
know, then it's the father one takes the precedence, right? That's so,
but I very much like those explanation of that. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this. איבעיא
להו, Ibe'u Lehu, there is the following question. רוכב כמהלך דמי או
לא? Rochaiv Kimahalich Dami O Lo? Is somebody if somebody is walking
by on a donkey now we had this story before about אביי,
Abaye, so I'm not exactly sure why the גמרא Gemara doesn't refer
to that. But if somebody, if a רבי Rebbe is walking is
riding by on a donkey is that like he walked into the
room? Now I'm not exactly sure again what the question is, because
it says, you know, מפני שיבה תקום והדרת פני זקן. Mipnei Seiva
Takum Vehadarta Pnei Zakein. It doesn't say if this person is walking
into the room, you stand up, right? It just says you get
up. So, you know, he appeared in my presence. What difference does
it make that he's sitting down? Right? He still appeared in my
presence. Right? I don't understand. Let's say he was on a you
know, on a one of those
flatbed type of you know, those things that have wheels on them
that are used for moving, right? And he was like pushing himself
along. Let's say it was like, whatever, he's in a wheelchair or
something and he was, you know, and he was just moving into
the room. Well, he's not he didn't walk into the room. I
mean, what difference does it make? הדרת פני זקן. Hadarta Pnei Zakein.
I really don't understand exactly the question of the גמרא. Gemara. You
know, maybe the idea is that standing is only meaningful if he's
standing? I don't understand why. Anyway, I don't understand why it matters.
But okay.
But maybe it's because he's in a seated position, it's not like
he entered, it's more like he's just present. I don't know. עולא.
Olo. אמר אביי Amar Abaye now אביי Abaye remember was the one
who was on his donkey and he was upset that the other
student didn't that students didn't stand for him. תא שמע, Ta Shma,
come in here. טמא יושב תחת האילן וטהור עומד טמא. Tamei Yoshev
Tahat Ha'ilan Vetahor Omed Tamei. So here's a הלכה halacha about a
מצורע. metzora. That if a מצורע metzora basically is the הלכה halacha
is that if a if that if a מצורע metzora and a
טהור tahor person are in the same, you know, room, under the
same roof, then the טהור tahor person is טמא, tamei, but it's
not like מת meis where it works with straight טומאת אהל. tumat
ohel. Only if the מצורע metzora is sitting. If the מצורע metzora
is like moving or standing, it doesn't the person under the tree
or under the roof does not become טמא. tamei. So טמא יושב
Tamei Yoshev if the טמא tamei person is sitting תחת האילן Tahat
Ha'ilan וטהור עומד Vetahor Omed and the טהור tahor person is standing,
טמא. Tamei. Then he's טמא. tamei. Because the issue is that the
טמא tamei person has to be sitting. טמא עומד תחת האילן וטהור
יושב, Tamei Omed Tahat Ha'ilan Vetahor Yoshev, if the טמא tamei is
standing, okay, not even walking, just standing, and the טהור tahor is
sitting, טהור. Tahor. So the טמא tamei person has to be sitting.
אם ישב הטמא, Im Yashav HaTamei, but if then the טמא tamei
person chooses to sit down, הטהור טמא, HaTahor Tamei, then he becomes
טמא. tamei. There's so many טמא tameis and טהור tahors here, it's
hard, you know, you gotta learn how to parse this. וכן באבן
המנוגעת. Vechein Be'even Hamenuga'at. And the same is true if it's not
we're talking about a person who is a מצורע, metzora, but a
stone that has צרעת, tzara'at, that is being carried under a tree.
Okay? So this week's פרשה. parsha. So if the stone is being
carried under the tree, so if the person holding the stone is
standing, the people under the tree are טהור. tahor. But if the
person holding the stone is sitting, the people under the tree are
טמא. tamei. So what so how's this relevant? ואמר רב נחמן בר
כהן, Ve'amar Rav Nachman Bar Kohen, זאת אומרת, Zot Omeret, this tells
you רוכב כמהלך דמי. Rochaiv Kimahalich Dami. That riding is like moving.
Why does it tell you riding is like moving? Because the stone
is you know, the stone isn't moving, it's just being moved. And
nevertheless, the identity of the stone is defined by the one that
is conveying it. So if the one that is conveying it is
standing, it's like the stone is standing. If the one that is
conveying it is moving, it's like or sitting or whatever sitting is
like the stone is sitting. And if the one is moving, it's
like the stone is moving. So you see, the status of the
stone is like the thing underneath it. I have no idea how
this is relevant at all. Excuse me. First of all, there's the
question of standing versus sitting, which is both are stationary, as opposed
to moving versus sitting versus standing.
And as I said, what does this issue why should it be
relevant and where do you even get the idea that by והדרת
פני זקן Hadarta Pnei Zakein it has to it's relevant sitting versus
standing? It should be, you know, I don't begin to understand this
גמרא. Gemara. Anyway, moving on.
איבעיא להו. Ibe'u Lehu. מהו לעמוד מפני ספר תורה? Mahu La'amod Mipnei
Sefer Torah? Do you stand in the presence of a ספר תורה?
Sefer Torah? So רב חילקיא ורב סימון ורב
אלעזר Rav Hilkiya VeRav Simon VeRav Elazar אמר קל וחומר. Amar Kal
Vachomer. מקל וחומר Mi-kal vachomer they do. מפני לומדיה עומדים מפניה לא
כל שכן? Mipnei Lomdeha Omdim Mipaneha Lo Kol Shekein?
If you stand before those who learn תורה, Torah, certainly you stand
before the תורה Torah itself.
Go the other way around. Why?
Because meaning like the whole point of the תורה Torah is to
be internalized. In other words, like, you know, like wasn't there this
whole thing like I remember this other גמרא Gemara like... These people
are so silly that they stand in front of the ספר תורה
Sefer Torah but not in front of the תלמידי חכמים Talmidei Chachamim
because the תלמידי
חכמים
Talmidei
Chachamim can get you from 40 מכות, makkot, 40 lashes to 39.
Right. Exactly. The power of תורה שבעל פה, Torah she-ba'al peh, our
involvement, right? And you know, right, and also what it means to
sort of take it out of sort of the thing that, you
know, to make it alive and to transmit it and to, you
know, exactly. But here's that's the way this, what's this position is
saying. רבי אלעאי רבי יעקב בר זבידי Rabbi Ilai Rabbi Yaakov bar
Zvidi הוו יתבי. havei yatvei. They were sitting. חליף ואזיל רבי שמעון
בר אבא chalif v'azil Rabbi Shimon bar Abba וקמו מקמיה. v'kumu mikameih.
רבי שמעון בר אבא Rabbi Shimon bar Abba passed by and they
stood in front of him. אמר להו
חדא דאתון חכימי ואנא חבר. amar lehu chada d'atun chakimei v'ana chaver.
So he said to them, first of all, I don't understand why
you stood before me. First of all, you're חכימי chakimei and I'm
just a חבר. chaver. A חבר chaver is somebody of like status
in the community, maybe somewhat of a בעל מעשים, baal ma'asim, like
we saw before, but not תלמידי חכמים, Talmidei Chachamim, so why did
you stand before me? ועוד v'od and number two, כלום תורה עומדת
מפני לומדיה? klum Torah omedet mipnei lomdeha? Does תורה Torah stand up
in the presence of its learners? Now what does that mean? Does
it mean so the way רש"י Rashi says what it means is,
is that, well the גמרא Gemara is going to say. סבר לה
כרבי אלעזר, savar lah k'Rabbi Elazar, דאמר רבי אלעזר, d'amar Rabbi Elazar,
אין תלמיד חכם רשאי לעמוד מפני רבו בשעה שעוסק בתורה. ein Talmid
Chacham rasha'i l'amod mipnei rabbo b'sha'ah she'osek ba-Torah. That a תלמיד חכם
Talmid Chacham cannot stand in front of his רבי Rebbe when he
is learning תורה. Torah. So for them, they were learning תורה Torah
and they interrupted their תורה Torah to stand in his presence. So
he said the actual learning of תורה, Torah, like is like the
ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. That's like תורה Torah itself, right? So by
interrupting your תורה Torah and standing, you're having תורה Torah stand before
me, I'm just a learner of תורה. Torah. תורה Torah was actually
coming out of your mouths, you know, it was the חפצא cheftza
of תורה Torah we would say, and then you had that תורה
Torah show feel, like show reverence, to me and I'm just a
learner of תורה. Torah. Okay, so the תורה Torah does not show
reverence to the learner of תורה. Torah. Says the גמרא Gemara says,
now the גמרא Gemara ends by saying לייט עלה אביי. laite lah
Abaye. But אביי Abaye would like curse this practice of רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar that says that if you're learning תורה, Torah, you don't
stand up in front of a תלמיד חכם. Talmid Chacham. And I
think that this, and he said that's absolutely wrong, even if you're
learning תורה Torah you stand up in front of a תלמיד חכם.
Talmid Chacham. And I think that this is, you know, the point
that Dov said before, I was thinking the same point but I
was thinking about this גמרא, Gemara, which is that what does it
mean that if you're learning תורה Torah and you're at and and
you can't show respect to a תורה Torah sage while you're learning
תורה? Torah? What does that say about the תורה Torah that you're
learning, right? So that's actually here. So that's again, like to show
כבוד kavod to the ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, you could make a
קל וחומר, kal vachomer, but that doesn't mean that if you're learning
תורה Torah you say oh well that's more important than the תלמיד
חכם Talmid Chacham and I'm not going to show כבוד kavod to
the תלמיד חכם. Talmid Chacham. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara ends
this by saying והביטו אחרי משה באהל אהלו, v'hibitu acharei Moshe b'ohel
olo,
they would look towards משה Moshe until he went into the tent.
רבי אמי רבי יצחק נפחא, Rabbi Ammi Rabbi Yitzchak Nafcha, חד אמר
לגנאי וחד אמר לשבח. chad amar l'gnai v'chad amar l'shvach. One reads
this derogatorily, how they behaved, and one says in praiseworthy. מאן דאמר
לגנאי, man d'amar l'gnai, כדיתא. k'di itah. Like like we know. רש"י
Rashi says the גמרא Gemara didn't want to elaborate because it was
like a nasty statement. According to the מדרש, Midrash, basically looked after
משה, Moshe, they were like making comments about him. They were saying
oh look how fat he is, look how whatever he is, it's
all because he he takes advantage of us, you know, he he
got wealthy from us. So they would make like this never happens
anywhere else that people make actually complaints and comments about their רבי.
Rebbe. So that's one version of it. And the other one says
לשבח. l'shvach. So what's לשבח? l'shvach? מאן דאמר לשבח, man d'amar l'shvach,
חזקיה אמר ואי תימא רבי חנינא בריה דרבי אבהו אמר רבי אבהו
אמר רבי אבדימי דמן חיפה, Chizkiyah amar v'it teima Rabbi Chanina breih
d'Rabbi Abbahu amar Rabbi Abbahu amar Rabbi Avdimi d'min Haifa, חכם עובר,
chacham over, now we get to some הלכה halakhah which we're going
to base on this connect to this פסוק, pasuk, חכם עובר עומד
מלפניו ארבע אמות. chacham over omed milfanav arba amot.
So then you stand when he comes within your
ארבע אמות. arba amot. וכיון שעבר ארבע אמות v'keivan she-avar arba amot
יושב, yoshev, you can sit back down. אב בית דין עובר, Av
Beis Din over,
if however it's not just a חכם chacham but the head of
the בית דין, Beis Din, then עומד מלפניו מלא עיניו. omed milfanav
melo einav. Then as soon as you see him, which again we
sort of pointed out the irony because more כבוד kavod is shown
when he gets nearer and you stand up, but you know as
was pointed out the other day, maybe the whole you know the
whole sort of your own מידה middah that you you need to
stand, not for him. Anyway, as soon as you see
him. וכיון שעבר ארבע אמות v'keivan she-avar arba amot יושב, yoshev, then
you can go back and sit down.
What does that mean?
He enters the room or he you see him at the other
end of the street, you stand up, he's coming your way, once
he gets ארבע אמות arba amot out of your way behind you,
right, or he comes in that end of the room, the whole
בית מדרש Beis Medrash stands up for the רבי, Rebbe once the
רבי Rebbe passes me and he gets out of my ארבע אמות,
arba amot, right, then I stood until he went out of from
the time he entered my zone, my sight zone, until he left
my space zone. Okay.
Is he your רבי, Rabbi. חכם עובר עומד? chacham over omed?
No, חכם, chacham, again, we're back to like any חכם. chacham.
אב בית דין
Av
Beis
Din though would be מלא עיניו?
melo einav? Well, that's what we're going to get. Keep on reading.
נשיא עובר עומד מלפניו מלא עיניו ואינו יושב עד שישב במקומו. Nasi
over omed milfanav melo einav v'eino yoshev ad she-yeshev bimkomo.
Okay, but if it's a נשיא, Nasi, actually we're framing משה Moshe
here as the נשיא, Nasi, okay, which again what does that mean?
It's the higher, it seems now sort of the political dimension, not
just the תורה Torah dimension, okay? You don't sit until the רבי
Rebbe, or the נשיא Nasi actually is seated himself.
שנאמר והביטו אחרי משה. she-ne'emar v'hibitu acharei Moshe. I think that
the—Right, you're going back to the question about standing before your father.
Hold on. Let me just see very quickly.
One minute.
Yeah, the רמבם Rambam does not distinguish
between a רבי Rebbe and רבו מובהק rabo muvkhak in terms of
standing.
So that's interesting. In terms of the issue about the father...
In terms of the issue about the father, let me just see
quickly
the
שולחן ערוך
Shulchan Aruch here.
No, he—the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch says: חייב לעמוד מפני אביו. chayav
la'amod mifnei aviv.
I think he's just getting this—he's getting this just implicitly from this
גמרא. Gemara. I mean, it's interesting that it didn't come up in
the earlier גמרות. Gemaros. There is that story about the רבי Rebbe,
that gets up and says, "Here's his mother coming, the שכינה Shekhinah
is coming," but here it just says חייב לעמוד מפני אביו chayav
la'amod mifnei aviv and I think he's just getting it implicitly. I
don't know, I think there are some communities where they do.
Is it understood that your parents are מוחל mochel this or not?
Maybe. Probably in most of our places we assume that they're מוחל.
mochel. Okay, but you're right, I mean, it's implicit in this גמרא
Gemara but the גמרא Gemara never said it directly in discussions of
כיבוד אב ואם. kibbud av va'em. Okay, let's continue.
And it would be your mother too.
Yeah, and father—that's an important point to remember also because all we
wind up talking about father, father, father, and particular when we talk
about things that are more about status and יראה yirah and authority,
we know, we know, but of course the גמרא Gemara before points
out that's why the תורה Torah emphasized מורא אם moras em first,
to know that that same is true about the mother, right? Okay,
now we move on completely switching gears to this big issue about
the מצות עשה שהזמן גרמה mitzvas asei she-hazeman grama that women are
exempt from. כל מצות עשה שהזמן גרמה, Kol mitzvas asei she-hazeman grama,
any time-bound מצוה, mitzvah, men are obligated and women are exempt. תנו
רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: איזו היא מצות עשה שהזמן גרמה? eizo hi mitzvas
asei she-hazeman grama? What would be an example of this? סוכה ולולב
שופר וציצית ותפילין.
Sukkah ve-lulav
shofar ve-tzitzis ve-tefillin. Okay, those are a good couple of examples. ציצית
Tzitzis and תפילין tefillin presumably because ציצית tzitzis doesn't apply at night,
תפילין tefillin because תפילין tefillin maybe doesn't apply at night and doesn't
apply on שבת. Shabbos. I'll say two things about that: first of
all, תוספות Tosafos has a whole discussion—he says ציצית tzitzis does apply
at night,
it's just it doesn't apply to nighttime garments, but if you're wearing
a day garment at night it applies, so why is that called
זמן גרמה? zeman grama? So תוספות Tosafos says, "Well, it must be
that we see from this that זמן גרמה zeman grama doesn't mean
that the מצוה mitzvah only applies at certain times but it means
that the time—the issue of time affects the scope of the מצוה."
mitzvah. So since because garments that are night garments don't have ציצית,
tzitzis, that means that time is a factor in which type of
garments are obligated in ציצית, tzitzis, okay? But that becomes now a
very funny definition. How about תפילין? tefillin? תוספות Tosafos says if we
פוסקין pasken that nighttime is זמן תפילין zeman tefillin and you just
don't wear it at night because you're afraid you'll פאסט גאז, pas-gas,
then the only time you don't wear תפילין tefillin is שבת. Shabbos.
So he says, "Would if you hadn't already bought into the idea
that that's מצות עשה שהזמן גרמה, mitzvas asei she-hazeman grama, would you
say that's מצות עשה שהזמן גרמה? mitzvas asei she-hazeman grama? I wouldn't.
I would say that fundamentally you're always obligated to wear תפילין tefillin
and there are some times where you're exempt, right? But no, because
it's not constant, now it becomes זמן גרמה." zeman grama. So we
wind up like redefining what זמן גרמה zeman grama means. Okay, now
the גמרא Gemara continues: ואיזו היא מצות עשה שלא הזמן גרמה? ve-eizo
hi mitzvas asei she-lo hazeman grama? What's considered not time-bound? So מזוזה
מעקה אבידה ושילוח הקן. mezuzah ma'akeh aveidah ve-shiluach ha-ken.
Okay, so your מזוזה mezuzah and a—a thing around your—what do you
call it?—around your roof, a fence around your roof, and returning a
lost object, and sending away the mother bird. Now תוספות Tosafos says
it's a very funny list that the גמרא Gemara gives because with
the exemption—exception of מזוזה, mezuzah, every single one of those is connected
to a לא תעשה, lo sa'aseh, right? It says by אבידה aveidah
it says לא תוכל להתעלם, lo tuchal le-his'alem, you cannot hide yourself
from it, and sending away the mother bird it says
שלח
תשלח shalle'ach teshallach but it says לא תקח האם על הבנים. lo
sikach ha-em al ha-banim. Okay, and מעקה ma'akeh it says—מצות עשה
שהזמן גרמה, mitzvas asei she-zeman grama, women would be obligated in a
לא תעשה... lo sa'aseh...
what? So תוספות's Tosafos question is—and לא תשים דמים בביתך lo sasim
damim be-veisecha by מעקה. ma'akeh. So תוספות's Tosafos question is like twofold:
you could sort of say like even if it weren't—even if they
weren't obligated in the מצות עשה, mitzvas asei, they'd have to be
doing this because of the לא תעשה. lo sa'aseh. And another sort
of way to say—well מזוזה mezuzah fine but he's asking about the
three of the four. And the other way of asking the question
is that he says like, you know, sort of like we say
that—and this even
stronger—like if we say like, oh, women are—start told that they can't
eat מצה, matzah, so they have to eat—that they can't eat חמץ,
chametz, so they have to eat מצה matzah like... Like one would
think that the quality of a מצוות עשה mitzvas aseh that is
linked to a לא תעשה lo sasei is a different type. Like
I get, tell me anytime there's a לא תעשה, lo sasei, of
course they're also חייב chayav in the עשה, aseh, right? But the
סתם עשה stam aseh by itself, that's a different story. But here
it sort of comes as a package. So תוספות Tosafos tries to
find cases where you would just have the עשה aseh without the
לא תעשה. lo sasei. Like by the אבידה aveida he said, let's
say I would pick up the אבידה aveida with the intent to
return it, and then I changed my mind. So that wouldn't be
לא תוכל להתעלם, lo suchal l'hitalem, but it would still be a
מצווה mitzvah of השב תשיבם. hasheiv tishivum. Or let's say I built
the fence on my roof, and then the fence fell down. So
it wouldn't be לא תשים דמים בביתך lo sasim damim b'veisecha because
I made—I did initially respond to the situation, but it would still
be ועשית מעקה. va'asisa ma'akeh. Okay, so he finds these scenarios, but
bottom line is it was a really good question because even if
you could separate them, you could still say that they're fundamentally of
a different quality than something that's just a stand-alone מצוות עשה. mitzvas
aseh. So it is interesting that the גמרא Gemara gives all of
these examples.
I know none of—you're right that these are only—but listen to—making a
ברכה? bracha? That's not considered a מצוות עשה שהזמן גרמא mitzvas aseh
shezman grama even though it's only triggered by things that I do
at a certain point.
Right, but again, things that can happen at any time but are
not related to this specific time of day or time on the
calendar is not זמן גרמא. zman grama. The opposite of זמן גרמא
zman grama is not constant. It just means that it's not linked
to time.
Like מזוזה, Mezuzah, you always have to have it. ציצית, Tzitzis, you
always have to have it.
No, but אבידה aveida is when you see an אבידה. aveida. שילוח
הקן shiluach hakan is when—קן ken is when you see the bird
nest. So that's worth pointing out that מצוות עשה שלא הזמן גרמא
mitzvas aseh shelo zman grama does not mean constant. It just means
it's not based on calendar and time of day. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this: וכללא הוא? v'klala hu? Is this
כלל klal really work? Does this really, you know, explain what they're
obligated and what they're exempt from? הרי, Harei, מצה, Matzo, שמחה, Simcha,
הקהל. Hakhel. Here are three מצוות, mitzvos, eating מצה, Matzo, ושמחת בחגך,
v'samachta b'chagecha, you—מצה—לא תוכל
חמץ, chametz מצה, Matzo right?
Yeah, yeah, מצה, matzo, like the מצוות מצה—I
mitzvas matzo thought you were saying the פסוק pasuk for—No.
And then שמחה. Simcha. מצה matzo, is מצוות מצה mitzvas matzo of
סדר Seder night. שמחה Simcha is, you know, it says,
אתה—what's the פסוק? pasuk.
ושמחת בחגך אתה ובנך ובתך.
v'samachta b'chagecha
ata
uvincha uvitecha.
אתה ובנך ובתך—ובתך זהו אשתך, I think. I think—no, I think that's
the
פסוק. Pasuk And—where are we?
Yeah. ושמחת בחגך אתה ובנך ובתך. v'samachta b'chagecha ata uvincha uvitecha. רש"י
Rashi says אתה—רש"י Rashi doesn't even quote ובתך. uvitecha. רש"י Rashi just
says אתה ובנך ובתך—ובתך, maybe it's ביתך bitecha's where we're learning it
from. Okay, anyway. And הקהל. Hakhel. Okay, where it explicitly says women
come to הקהל. Hakhel. Three מצוות עשה שהזמן גרמא mitzvas aseh shezman
grama that's only in certain times, ונשים חייבות, v'nashim chayavos, and they're
obligated to. So that's cases where it's time-bound and they're obligated. Now
I'll give you cases where it's not time-bound that they're exempt. הרי
תלמוד תורה פריה ורביה פדיון הבן. Harei Talmud Torah, Pirya v'Rivya, Pidyon
HaBen. So תלמוד תורה, Talmud Torah, which is constant. פריה ורביה, Pirya
v'Rivya, which is, you know, again, it might start only when a
person
is
of—you know—able to have kids, but nevertheless, it's basically not based on
calendar and time of day. And פדיון הבן, Pidyon HaBen, which also
starts on day 30 but then is ongoing. Okay, דלאו מצוות עשה
שהזמן גרמא, d'lav mitzvas aseh shezman grama, that's not considered
time-bound, ונשים פטורות, v'nashim paturos, and women are exempt. Of course, the
one we haven't discussed was פריה ורביה. Pirya v'Rivya. We discussed it
back in יבמות, Yevamos, but the others we discussed. Anyway, so this
כלל klal doesn't work in either direction. So the גמרא Gemara says:
אמר רבי יוחנן אין למדין מן הכללות ואפילו במקום שנאמר בו חוץ.
amar Rabbi Yochanan ein l'meidim min haklalos v'afilu b'makom shena'amar bo chutz.
You cannot learn from general statements even when certain exceptions are listed.
You know—here's the general principle with the following exceptions. So you would
think if you're going to tell me the exceptions, then it means
it's always true in all other cases. No. You can never trust
a general principle. Okay, so—I don't know, it's a general guideline, but
it's never—it's not 100 percent. And even if you're giving exceptions, they
might not be all the exceptions. Okay, דתנן, detnan, בכל מערבין ומשתתפין.
b'chol me'arvin u'mishtatfin. You could make an עירוב. eiruv. רש"י Rashi says
it means עירוב חצירות, eiruv chatzeros, תוספות Tosafos say עירוב תחומין, eiruv
techumin, or שיתוף מבואות shittuf mevo'os by joining in together, you know,
in order to—in some shared food to allow carrying.
חוץ מן המים ומלח, chutz min hamayim u'melach, except for salt and
water, because those are not considered like sating and filling. ותו ליכא?
v'su leka? But are there no other things? ואיכא כמהין ופטריות. v'ika
k'mehin u'pitrios. How about fungi and mushrooms? אלא אין למדין מן הכללות,
ella, ein l'meidim min haklalos, you see, ואפילו במקום שנאמר בו חוץ.
v'afilu b'makom shena'amar bo chutz. Even if it says this is the
rule with the following exception, you can't trust it. There could be
other exceptions and it's not 100 percent of a rule. Now the
question still is, that's what the רמב"ם—when Rambam I read that in
the רמב"ם פירוש המשניות. Rambam Peirush Hamishnayos. Now the question is though,
what does that mean? Does it mean though this is generally the
rule that dictates, there's just lots and lots of exceptions? But אין
הכי נמי, ein hachinami, this is really, you know, a fundamental reason
why women are exempt unless you find another exemption? Or what does
it even mean? And one way of understanding this is like this
is just an easy way to describe and categorize. But really, this
is what the רמב"ם Rambam says in פירוש המשניות, Peirush Hamishnayos, everything
we know we just know separately from
מסורה. masorah. It's not like there's a rule that dictates, right? That's
a very important question because the general way the גמרא Gemara operates,
the סתם stam of the גמרא Gemara operates, is that this rule
does dictate. dictate that if you don't know what the הלכה Halacha
is, you can sort of like, you know, refer to the idea
that it's a מצוות עשה שהזמן גרמא Mitzvas Aseh Shehazman Gerama and
that should dictate that women should be exempt. So that it really
is that if that's that we should presume that anything that's a
מצוות עשה שהזמן גרמא Mitzvas Aseh Shehazman Gerama because it's a מצוות
עשה שהזמן גרמא Mitzvas Aseh Shehazman Gerama women should be exempt unless
you have some proof otherwise, which is very different than saying that
after the fact we look at the all the cases and we
sort of give this as some type of a descriptor, right? It's
very different to be an after the fact descriptor and a before
the fact reason for why women are, you know, predictor of why
women are exempt. And that's going to be the presumption of the
גמרא Gemara is the latter way. So let's keep on reading. Okay,
ומצוות עשה שהזמן גרמא נשים פטורות, U'mitzvas Aseh Shehazman Gerama Nashim P'turos,
women are exempt.
מנלן, Minalan, where do you know this from? גמר מתפילין. Gemar Mitfilin.
So now we get to the core, what's the whole source of
this? From תפילין. Tefillin. מה תפילין נשים פטורות, Mah Tefillin Nashim P'turos,
women are exempt. Of course we're going to have to ask how
we know women are exempt from תפילין. Tefillin. אף כל מצוות עשה
שהזמן גרמא נשים פטורות, Af Kol Mitzvas Aseh Shehazman Gerama Nashim P'turos,
everything, תפילין Tefillin is, becomes the paradigm. So we have two questions.
Number one is, how do you know תפילין Tefillin women are exempt?
And two, why do you choose תפילין Tefillin as the paradigm as
opposed to other things as the paradigm? Okay, so גמרא Gemara says
ותפילין גמר מתלמוד תורה. V'tefillin Gemar Mitalmud Torah. מה תלמוד תורה נשים
פטורות, Mah Talmud Torah Nashim P'turos, the same way תלמוד תורה Talmud
Torah where women are exempt, because it says בניכם B'neichem and we
read that's בניכם ולא בנותיכם. B'neichem V'lo B'noteichem.
נשים פטורות. Nashim P'turos. אף תפילין נשים פטורות, Af Tefillin Nashim P'turos,
even תפילין Tefillin women are exempt. Now of course you have to
point out the irony because תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah is not זמן
גרמא, Zman Gerama, right? So the פסוק Pasuk is, right, what's the
פסוק Pasuk by קריאת שמע? Krias Shema? Right, the פסוק pasuk by
the שמע Shema is what? ושיננתם לבניך ודברת בם בשבתך
בביתך
ובלכתך בדרך,
V'shinnantahm L'vanecha V'dibarta Bam B'shivtecha B'veitecha
U'v'lechtecha Vaderech, right,
right, ודברת בם בשבתך בביתך ובלכתך
בדרך,
V'dibarta Bam B'shivtecha B'veitecha
U'v'lechtecha Vaderech, etc. which is תורה Torah and then it says, right,
וקשרתם לאות על ידך והיו לטטפת
U'kshartam L'os Al
Yadecha V'hayu L'totafos
and then we're going to have וכתבתם U'chsavtam because that's going to
be מזוזה Mezuzah על מזוזות. Al Mezuzos. Okay, so here we're going
to have מזוזה. Mezuzah. Women are חייב Chayav or פטור Patur in
מזוזה? Mezuzah? חייב. Chayav. Thank you, thank you very much. Okay, תפילין,
Tefillin, women are חייב Chayav or פטור? Patur? פטור. Patur. Okay, תלמוד
תורה, Talmud Torah, women are פטור. Patur. Okay, so
we're
going to say we know women are פטור Patur here because of
בניכם, B'neichem, בניכם ולא בנותיכם. B'neichem V'lo B'noteichem.
We know women are פטור. Patur. Therefore they're פטור Patur here. Okay,
how do we know they're חייב Chayav in מזוזה? Mezuzah? Why don't
we just keep on going down the row? We'll find out. And
because they're פטור Patur here, we're going to say that this becomes
the paradigm that they're פטור Patur when it's, you know, מצוות עשה
שהזמן גרמא. Mitzvas Aseh Shehazman Gerama. Which is very ironic because if
it started here, say this is the paradigm and then they should
be פטור Patur from even מצוות עשה שלא הזמן גרמא. Mitzvas Aseh
Shelo Hazman Gerama. Okay, so we will, let's take a look where
the גמרא Gemara goes.
Okay. מה תפילין נשים פטורות אף כל מצוות עשה שהזמן גרמא נשים
פטורות. Mah Tefillin Nashim P'turos Af Kol Mitzvas Aseh Shehazman Gerama Nashim
P'turos. וניקש תפילין למזוזה? V'nikash Tefillin L'mezuzah? Why don't we say, wait
a minute, who told you that תפילין Tefillin are פטור? Patur? Maybe
תפילין Tefillin should be חייב Chayav the same way women are חייב
Chayav in מזוזה? Mezuzah? תפילין
לתלמוד תורה איתקש בין בפרשה ראשונה בין בפרשה שניה. Tefillin L'talmud Torah
Itkash Bein B'parsha Rishona Bein B'parsha Shniya. No, because in the first
פרשה Parsha you have תפילין Tefillin juxtaposed to תלמוד תורה, Talmud Torah,
okay? And in the second פרשה Parsha of קריאת שמע Krias Shema
it happens, תפילין למזוזה בפרשה שניה לא איתקש. Tefillin L'mezuzah B'parsha Shniya
Lo Itkash. But if you look in the second פרשה Parsha of
קריאת שמע, Krias Shema, it's not directly juxtaposed to מזוזה, Mezuzah, right?
Because the second פרשה Parsha of קריאת שמע Krias Shema reads: right,
so the
first פרשה Parsha is what we said, בשבתך
וקשרתם לאות על ידך וכתבתם על מזוזות ביתך. B'shivtecha U'kshartam L'os Al
Yadecha U'chsavtam Al Mezuzos Beitecha.
The second
פרשה Parsha of קריאת שמע Krias Shema is ושמתם את דברי אלה
על לבבכם ועל נפשכם וקשרתם אתם לאות על ידכם והיו לטטפת ולימדתם.
V'samtem Es Divray Eileh Al L'vavchem V'al Nafshechem U'kshartam Osam L'os
Al Yedchem V'hayu L'totafos V'limadetem. It reverses the order. First it has
וקשרתם, U'kshartam, then it has ולימדתם, V'limadetem,
and then it says וכתבתם. U'chsavtam. Right, so in the second פרשה
Parsha it says וקשרתם
ולימדתם
וכתבתם.
U'kshartam V'limadetem
U'chsavtam. So in the second פרשה Parsha תפילין Tefillin is linked to
תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah and it's too distant from מזוזה. Mezuzah. Okay,
so therefore the תפילין Tefillin is always linked to תלמוד תורה Talmud
Torah and it's not always linked to מזוזה, Mezuzah, so we're going
to learn it out from תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah that תפילין Tefillin
is פטור Patur and not חייב. Chayav. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara continues. Yeah, everybody with me? Okay.
Now the גמרא Gemara says: וניקש מזוזה לתלמוד תורה. V'neekash Mezuzah L'talmud
Torah. Okay, so now we've got that these two are always linked,
so these are פטור. Patur. So now let's go and continue and
say מזוזה Mezuzah should learn out from תפילין Tefillin or here מזוזה
Mezuzah should learn out from תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah. directly because they're
linked here. And let's say מזוזה Mezuzah also women are פטור. patur.
ונוקש מזוזה לתלמוד תורה. venekash Mezuzah leTalmud Torah. No, לא סלקא דעתך,
lo salka daitach, דכתיב למען ירבו ימיכם, dichsiv leman yirbu yemeichem, in
order that your days should increase. גברי בעי חיי נשי לא בעי
חיי? gavrei bei chayei neshei lo bei chayei? What, only men need
life, women don't need life? So because מזוזה Mezuzah says למען ירבו
ימיכם, leman yirbu yemeichem, obviously women are חייב. chayav.
Of course תוספות Tosafot points
out, תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah also says למען ירבו ימיכם, leman yirbu
yemeichem, so women should be חייב. chayav. Ah, but there it's בניכם
ולא בנותיכם. beneichem velo benoteichem. So sort of like this tips the
scales
when we don't know what the הלכה halacha is going to be.
Okay, since we don't know, we're going to presume that women are
going to be חייב, chayav, but if we have a special דרשה
drasha like בניכם ולא בנותיכם, beneichem velo benoteichem, then women are going
to be exempt. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
okay, so now we've got how this breaks down, how we know
this, but and that we've chosen this as our paradigm, which is
ironic because it was learned from this, but we've chosen this as
our paradigm to say מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא. mitzvot asei shehazman grama.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this, סוכה Sukkah is a מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא, mitzvot asei shehazman
grama, דכתיב בסוכות תשבו שבעת ימים, dichsiv basukkot teshvu shivat yamim, סוכה
Sukkah is time-bound. טעמא דכתב רחמנא האזרח, ta'ama dechasav Rachmana ha'ezrach, and
it says כל האזרח בישראל, kol ha'ezrach beyisrael, all citizens. So what's
the word אזרח ezrach doing? להוציא את הנשים. lehotzi et hanashim. So
one of the דרשה drasha is אזרח ezrach means women are exempt.
So now the question is, הלאו הכי נשים חייבות? halav hachi nashim
chayavot? Why don't we say that since you needed a פסוק pasuk.
to exempt women by סוכה, Sukkah, you see that the general rule
is that women are obligated in מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא, mitzvot asei
shehazman grama, right? Assuming that that rule really dictates the, dictates each
individual case. All right, so oh, maybe we should learn from the
need to exempt women by סוכה Sukkah that the rule is that
women are חייב chayav in מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא. mitzvot asei shehazman
grama. But says no, אמר אביי איצטריך, Amar Abaye itzterich, no, you
needed that to be said there. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka daitach amina,
I would have thought, הא דכתיב תשבו, ha dichsiv teshvu, תשבו כעין
תדורו, teshvu ke'ein taduru, if you dwell, you dwell like you dwell
in your house. מה דירה איש ואשתו אף סוכה איש ואשתו, ma
dira ish ve'ishto af Sukkah ish ve'ishto, husband and wife dwell together,
eat together, sleep together, so
תשבו teshvu overcome מצות עשה
שהזמן גרמא.
mitzvot
asei shehazman grama.
I would have thought right, I would have thought that yeah maybe,
no I know מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא, mitzvot asei shehazman grama, that
rule is in place, but I would have thought תשבו teshvu would
have demanded women to be obligated. So therefore you needed האזרח, ha'ezrach,
but that does not tell you that the rule is different than
you thought the rule was. The rule still is, I would have
thought סוכה Sukkah there's a special reason women should be חייב, chayav,
but the general rule is women are exempt from a time-bound מצוה.
mitzvah. ורבא אמר איצטריך, ve'Rava amar itzterich, now Rava said you need
it. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka daitach amina, I would have thought, נילף
חמשה עשר חמשה עשר מחג המצות, neilef chamisha asar chamisha asar mechag
hamatzot, make a גזירה שוה gezeira shava because it both says here
on the fifteenth day you sit in a סוכה, Sukkah, on the
fifteenth day you eat a מצה, Matzo so מה להלן נשים חייבות,
ma lehalan nashim chayavot, the same way women are obligated in מצה
Matzah, because since women are prohibited against חמץ chametz we link the
prohibition of חמץ to the מצוה mitzvah of eating מצה. Matzah
So since they're obligated in מצה, Matzah. I would have said אף
כאן נשים חייבות, af kan nashim chayavot, women should be obligated in
eating in the סוכה. Sukkah. So איצטריך, itzterich, so you needed to
exempt them. But even though women needed to be exempted by סוכה,
Sukkah, that doesn't say that the rule is not what we thought
it was. The rule still is, I would have thought סוכה Sukkah
there's a special reason women should be חייב, chayav, but the general
rule is women are exempt from a time-bound מצוה. mitzvah. By the
way, since מצה Matzah, is coming up, since פסח Pesach is coming
up, I'll say something about this link between מצה Matzah and סוכה.
Sukkah. There's actually an interesting מחלוקת ראשונים machlokes Rishonim around this. You
know סוכה Sukkah in general you're exempt when it's raining out because
it's not considered like a normal way of living in a place
to be eating while it's raining. But some ראשונים Rishonim say that
on the first night you have to eat even if it's raining
because it's linked to מצה Matzah and therefore that sort of shows
this like absolute obligation. Right,
anyway so that's interesting about that link. But nevertheless women are exempt,
that's why you needed the פסוק. pasuk So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this, okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, הרי
ראיה, harei re'iya, זה מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא, zeh mitzvot asei shehazman
grama, wait a minute. Here's another place where if this rule really
applies I can again ask why did I need the פסוק pasuk
to tell me each this following
case? There's עולת ראיה, olat re'iya, appearing three times on the רגלים
regalim bringing a קרבן, korban, a קרבן. korban. זה מצות עשה שהזמן
גרמא, zeh mitzvot asei shehazman grama, it's time-bound. What more מצות עשה
שהזמן גרמא mitzvot asei shehazman grama do you have than a three
times a year
pilgrimage? וטעמא דכתב רחמנא זכורך, veta'ama dechasav Rachmana zechurcha, it says יראה
כל זכורך, yera'eh kol zechurcha, all of your males should appear, להוציא
את הנשים lehotzi et hanashim to exclude females, women. הלאו הכי נשים
חייבות, halav hachi nashim chayavot, so presumably though the rule would have
been if the תורה Torah had to spell out men are exempt,
I should, it seems like the rule would have been women should
have been obligated. So that seems to show that women are obligated
even in time-bound מצוות, mitzvot, or else why did the פסוק pasuk
have to spell it out here? No, איצטריך, itzterich, it had to
spell it out. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka daitach amina, I would have
thought, נילף ראיה ראיה מהקהל, neilef re'iya re'iya me'hakhel, that since women
are obligated in הקהל, hakhel, it says explicitly women, and it says
there also shall appear, and here it says shall appear יראה, yera'eh,
so maybe I would say the same way they have to
appear to hear הקהל hakhel for the gathering every seven years they
have to appear for the רגלים. regalim. So it had to say
no no no no no don't learn out from הקהל, hakhel, they're
exempt.
Which indicates you can make a גזירה שוה gezeira shava on your
own and I thought it has to be a מסורה mesora meaning
I would have done it but you can't.
That's a good point, I don't know the answer, it's a good
point. Okay, ודאפינן v'da'afneinan fine, so now the גמרא Gemara dealt with
a side issue which is if this rule. really applies why does
it ever have to say it explicitly in the following cases? Okay
that was a parenthetical question but now let's get back to the
basic point that תפילין tefillin is
our paradigm. And the other obvious questions there are so many other
cases why are we choosing תפילין tefillin as the paradigm? Right there's
other cases too. So now let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. The גמרא Gemara says like this.
ואדילפינן מתפילין לפטורא נילף משמחה לחיובא. ve-adyalfinan mi-tefillin le-ptura neleaf mi-simcha le-chiyuva.
One minute let's look at a מצוה mitzvah that's time bound that
women are obligated. What are the three מצוות mitzvot that we mentioned
that are time bound that women are obligated?
מצה שמחה והקהל matzah simcha ve-hakhel and let's say that those are
the paradigms that women are obligated in time bound מצוות mitzvot right?
Okay so why don't we learn out? So let's go through them.
Let's learn out from שמחה simcha that women are obligated in time
bound מצוות. mitzvot. אמר אביי אשה בעלה משמחה. amar abaye isha ba-alah
mesamchah. No no no women are not personally obligated in שמחה. simcha.
It's ושמחת אתה וביתך. ve-samachta atah u-beitecha. You the man have to
be משמח mesame'ach your household. It's not that your wife is obligated
in שמחה simcha you are obligated for your whole household okay?
So we throw out one of the three?
Yeah basically. Or if it's in the list but it's not a
real exception. Okay. By the way interesting רש"י תוספות. Rashi Tosafot. רש"י
Rashi says what it means to be משמח mesame'ach is like buy
her nice clothes or whatever nice food. But תוספות Tosafot says yeah
but that's only nowadays. בזמן שבית המקדש קיים bi-zman she-beit ha-mikdash kayam
let's not forget that שמחה simcha meant bringing שלמי שמחה shalmei simcha
you bring those קרבנות. korbanot. So תוספות Tosafot says what it means
is the husband is obligated to bring the קרבנות korbanot and to
share the meat of those קרבנות korbanot with the members of his
household. But it's not the woman's obligation okay. So that's what אביי
Abaye says. ואמר אמימר ve-amar amimar what if she's a widow? So
בשרויה אצלו. bi-shruyah etzlo. Because how do you know that a widow
is obligated? Because it says והגר והיתום והאלמנה אשר בקרבך ve-ha-ger ve-ha-yatom
ve-ha-almanah asher be-kirbecha right you should be משמח mesame'ach with the you
know sojourner with the stranger and the אלמנה. almanah. So fine. What
it means is the same thing as הגר. ha-ger. What it means
is like if you have a widow that is somehow dwelling among
you you know your neighbor someone in your household or whatever it
is then you have a responsibility your mother you have a responsibility
in those cases to be משמח mesame'ach as a member of your
household but not that she has a personal obligation. Okay so שמחה
simcha is not really an exception anyway. So now the
גמרא Gemara says okay ונילף מהקהל. ve-neleaf mi-hakhel. We still have two
other things that could serve as our paradigm הקהל hakhel and מצה.
Matzah Let's learn out from הקהל. hakhel. So now we're going to
use those two we're going to you know off one another okay.
משום דהוו מצה והקהל שני כתובים הבאים כאחד וכל שני כתובים הבאים
כאחד אין מלמדין. mishum de-havei matzah ve-hakhel shnei ketuvim ha-ba'im ke-echad ve-chol
shnei ketuvim ha-ba'im ke-echad ein melamdin. Yeah good you got two you
got two cases. So those two cases mean you can't learn from
either of them because the principle is if the תורה Torah says
something in two different places we should interpret those as exceptions rather
than the rule. Okay? So you have הקהל hakhel and you have
הקהל ומצה hakhel u-matzah and those neutralize one another all right. Now
אי הכי ei hachi says גמרא Gemara תפילין וראיה נמי שני כתובים
הבאים כאחד ואין מלמדין. tefillin ve-re'iyah nami shnei ketuvim ha-ba'im ke-echad ve-ein
melamdin. Okay so here are the cases right? So here's basically what
you have. Here are you know מצוות עשה שהזמן גרמה mitzvot asei
she-ha-zman gramah that women are exempt. What are they? What do we
have? We had תפילין. tefillin. What did it have what else did
the גמרא Gemara just say after
תפילין?
tefillin? וראיה. ve-re'iyah. סוכה לולב שופר ציצית. sukkah lulav shofar tzitzit.
Okay women right women are exempt. You know סוכה לולב sukkah lulav
yeah but some of those a lot of those aren't in the
פסוקים. pesukim. Right the ones that are in the פסוקים pesukim which
are the basis right are like שופר לולב וסוכה shofar lulav ve-sukkah
is in the פסוק based on the דרשה. derashah. ציצית ותפילין tzitzit
ve-tefillin aren't in it. Okay this is לא זמן גרמה lo zman
gramah right
לא הזמן גרמה lo ha-zman gramah that women are
that women are חייב. chayav. I'm sorry this is חייב chayav
and this is פטור. pattur. So the חייב chayav in the חייב
chayav category was was שמחה simcha which we sort of got rid
of הקהל hakhel and מצה. matzah. So which one should be the
paradigm? So we look at these and say women are חייב chayav
in time bound מצוות mitzvot or look at these and say women
are פטור. pattur. So we said well we don't look at these
because since there's two cases that are set explicitly they work off
one another. They're שני כתובים הבאים כאחד. shnei ketuvim ha-ba'im ke-echad. Okay.
So then let's not learn from any of these. Here we have
actually even three examples.
Okay yeah right three things that the תורה Torah say women are
exempt. I mean this is you know
if you can't learn from two you certainly can't learn from three.
So how does these become a paradigm? Let's just if these aren't
a paradigm to say you're חייב chayav these shouldn't be a paradigm
to say you're פטור. pattur. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. גמרא Gemara says אי הכי תפילין וראיה נמי שני כתובים הבאים
כאחד ואין מלמדין. ei hachi tefillin ve-re'iyah nami shnei ketuvim ha-ba'im ke-echad
ve-ein melamdin. צריכי. tzerichi.
No there you needed the תורה Torah to say it explicitly. דאי
כתב רחמנא de-ei katav rachamana anyway we already said why the תורה
Torah had to say סוכה. sukkah. It had to say סוכה sukkah
because of תשבו. teshvu. So because if the תורה Torah had to
say it then saying it doesn't make it an exception. Saying it
is a clarifying statement. So we already said why it had to
say סוכה sukkah and here's why it had to say תפילין. tefillin.
both of these cases. תפילין ואינמי צריכי. tefillin v'innami tzrichi. דאי כתב
רחמנא תפילין ולא כתב ראיה הוה אמינא נילף ראיה מהכא. de'ee kasav
Rachmana tefillin v'lo chasav re'iah hava amina nalleph re'iah me'haka.
It had to say explicitly by ראיה re'iah like we said before,
because if it had not said it by ראיה, re'iah, I would
have said, well, we learn that from הכא haka and we should
be חייב. chayav. So it had to say by ראיה re'iah that
women are exempt. דאי כתב רחמנא ראיה ולא כתב תפילין, de'ee kasav
Rachmana re'iah v'lo chasav tefillin, if it had just said ראיה, re'iah,
הוה אמינא אקש תפילין למזוזה, hava amina akish tefillin l'mezuzah, that I
would have said maybe תפילין tefillin should be, should be linked to
מזוזה, mezuzah, right? If it had not, if it had not linked
תפילין tefillin to תלמוד תורה, Talmud Torah, I would have linked it
to מזוזה. mezuzah. So therefore צריכא, tzricha, it had to say both.
So since each one of these were, every one was necessary, we're
going to learn of these as the rules and not the exceptions,
because each one had to be said. But here we're saying you
didn't have to say both. And since you didn't have to say
both, these are the exceptions. So these are the exceptions because it's
superfluous and these are the rules. So now we're going to say
why this was superfluous. אי הכי ee hachi says the גמרא, Gemara,
מצה והקהל נמי צריכי. matzah v'hakhel nami tzrichi. I could tell you
that you needed to say both מצה matzah. and הקהל hakhel and
those also should be rules and not exceptions. למה צריכי? lama tzrichi?
Why are they both needed? בשלמא אי כתב רחמנא הקהל bishlama ee
kasav Rachmana hakhel ולא כתב מצה, v'lo chasav matzah, הוה אמינא נילף
חמישה עשר חמישה עשר מחג הסוכות. hava amina nalleph chamisha asar chamisha
asar m'Chag HaSuccos.
I get why it had to say מצה. matzah Because if it
had not said by מצה matzah. that, excuse me, if it had
not said by מצה matzah that women are חייב, chayav, then I
would have learned out from סוכות Succos that women are exempt. So
therefore, because, because we know women are exempt from סוכות Succos because
האזרח, ha'ezrach, so therefore I could argue that it had to say
מצה matzah women are חייב chayav because otherwise I shouldn't learn out
from סוכה. succah. אלא הקהל, ela hakhel, but why by הקהל hakhel
did it have to say women are חייב? chayav? אלא נכתב רחמנא
מצה ולא בעי הקהל. ela nichtav Rachmana matzah v'lo ba'ee hakhel. Just
tell me מצה matzah and don't tell me הקהל. hakhel. How would
I have known anyway that women are חייב? chayav? ואנא אמינא, v'ana
amina, it's obvious. טפלים חייבים. tefelim chayavim.
If it says האנשים והנשים והטף, ha'anashim v'hanashim v'hatef, if infants are
חייב, chayav, נשים לא כל שכן? nashim lo kol shekein? Certainly women
should be חייב. chayav. Okay, so therefore says the גמרא, Gemara, this
is superfluous. הקהל hakhel did not have to tell me that women
are חייב. chayav. Just tell me women are חייב chayav in מצה,
matzah infants are חייב chayav in הקהל, hakhel, and of course women
would be חייב. chayav. So if you're still going to tell me
women are חייב, chayav, it's to point out that these are the
exceptions. These are the, and therefore you should know that the rule
is against this, and these are only being spelled out because they're
the exceptions. And this category, the פטור ptur category, is the rule.
And the reason it said it multiple times was each one was
needed to clarify something. But here we're superfluous. So the fact that
it was superfluous here makes it the exception, if it was being
spelled out, and here the פטור ptur category becomes the rule. Okay,
ואנא אמינא נשים לא כל שכן. v'ana amina nashim lo kol shekein.
הלכך הוו להו שני כתובים הבאים כאחד ואין מלמדין. hilkach havu lehu
shnei kesuvim habayim k'echad v'ein melamdin. Okay,
so amazingly we actually got pretty much caught up. And what we
have learned out now is the irony that we learned תפילין tefillin
from תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah and תפילין tefillin becomes the paradigm, even
though if we had made תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah the paradigm, we
would have said that women should be exempt from all מצוות עשה,
mitzvos asei, all מצוות עשה שהזמן גרמא. mitzvos asei she'hazman grama. But
somehow we got it down to here and then we made this
the paradigm. And then we said wait a minute, we have cases
of חיוב chiyuv of time-bound and cases of פטור. ptur. Which do
you decide is the paradigm? And it says these are the paradigms
because each one of these was necessary so these are not read
as exceptions. These are the exceptions because since some of this was
not necessary to be said, this rule is being read as the
exceptions rule, and
this list is the exceptions list, and this list is the rules
list. Okay, we will continue tomorrow.